<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<prayers>

    <item>
      <type>alef</type>
      <person>דין דין אביב, זמרת</person>
      <prayer>
כשביקרתי באומן, יצאתי בלילה במונית לשדה התעופה. כשהנהג המקומי עצר למלא דלק, גילינו שמיכל הדלק שלו קפא. הוא לא הצליח לפתוח אותו ולתדלק. בלית ברירה חזרנו לאומן, כדי שיוכל להחליף רכב. השעה היתה שתיים בלילה, המקום מפחיד ואני עם נהג שאני לא מכירה ולא מדבר אנגלית. אין איש בחוץ והשלג בגובה חצי מטר מעל האדמה. פתאום הנהג קם ונעלם. משאיר אותי בתוך האוטו, בדרכו להביא רכב חלופי. חמש דקות עברו, עשרים דקות, ואני קולטת שאני לא יודעת אם הנהג בכלל יחזור. לצאת מהאוטו? לנעול את עצמי בתוכו? להשאיר אור קטן? האם עדיף שיראו אותי או להפך? פחד גדול. והתפילה שיצאה ממני באותם רגעים היתה תפילת אמונה. אני באומן. הייתי אצל רבנו, אני בהשגחה שלו. העברתי את האחריות אליו. אמרתי, אני אצל הצדיק, לא יכול לקרות לי כלום. וכל הזמן הזה, כל מה שידעתי בעל פה – תפילה, תהלים, פסוקים מהתנ"ך – פשוט התחלתי למלמל וראיתי איך זה פועל עלי ומרגיע אותי. אלה היו רגעים של הישרדות. 
      </prayer>
    </item>

    <item>
      <type>alef</type>
      <person>אלברט איינשטיין, מדען</person>
      <prayer>
     מתוך הספר "פרופסור איינשטיין היקר: אלברט איינשטיין, מכתבים מאת ילדים ואליהם"

כנסיית ריברסייד, 19 בינואר 1936
ד"ר איינשטיין היקר שלי,
היתה לנו שאלה בבית הספר של יום א' שלנו: האם מדענים מתפללים? בהתחלה השאלה היתה אם אפשר להאמין גם במדע וגם בדת. אנחנו כותבים למדענים ולעוד אנשים חשובים כדי לנסות לקבל תשובה.
יהיה לנו לכבוד אם תענה על השאלה שלנו: האם מדענים מתפללים ולְמה הם מתפללים?
אנחנו בכיתה ו' של מיס אליס.
שלך בכבוד רב,
פיליס
----------------------
24 בינואר 1936
פיליס היקרה,
אנסה לענות על שאלתך בצורה הפשוטה ביותר שאני מסוגל לה. הנה התשובה שלי:
מדענים מאמינים שכל התרחשות, וענייניהם של בני האדם בכלל זה, מתרחשת מתוקף חוקי הטבע. לפיכך, מדענים אינם נוטים לסבור שאפשר להשפיע על מהלך האירועים באמצעות תפילה, כלומר, באמצעות משאלה המתגשמת באמצעים על-טבעיים.
עם זאת, אנחנו חייבים להודות שהידע הממשי שלנו באשר לכוחות האלה אינו מושלם, כך שבסופו של דבר ההנחה שקיימת רוח סופית ואולטימטיבית מתבססת על אמונה. אמונות כאלה היו ונותרו נפוצות למרות ההתקדמויות המדעיות האחרונות.
לצד זאת, כל מי שעסוק במדע בצורה רצינית מגיע למסקנה שבחוקי היקום ניכרת פעולתה של רוח כלשהי, העולה על האדם עשרות מונים. במובן זה, העיסוק במדע מוביל לרגש דתי מסוג מיוחד, כזה השונה בתכלית מן הדתיות של אנשים נאיבים יותר.
ברכות לבביות,
א. איינשטיין שלך
      </prayer>
    </item>

    <item>
      <type>alef</type>
      <person>יוסי אלפי, איש תיאטרון ומספר</person>
      <prayer>
       תְּפִלָּה

מִיּוֹם שֶׁלָּמַדְתִּי תְּפִלָּה
לָמַדְתִּי שָׁלוֹם עִם עַצְמִי
לָמַדְתִּי לְקַבֵּל וְלָתֵת וְלָקַחַת וּלְבַטֵּל
אֶת אִיּוּמַי

מִיּוֹם שֶׁלָּמַדְתִּי תְּפִלָּה
לָמַדְתִּי דְּלָתוֹת אֶל עַצְמִי
לָמַדְתִּי לִפְתֹּחַ וְלִקְשֹׁר 
וְאֶת חֲלוֹמִי לִפְתֹּר.


מתוך הספר "טביעות אצבע של אמא"
      </prayer>
    </item>

    <item>
      <type>alef</type>
      <person>קובי אפללו, זמר</person>
      <prayer>
      תפילה אישית לפני העלייה לבמה
 
אלי הטוב, קודם כל תודה על הזכות לשיר לקהל המעוניין להקשיב. זה לרגע לא מובן מאליו. אני תפילה שתזכך את קולי, שאדע לכוון נכון את לבי לנתינה בשירתי. שאעריך כל רגע ואשיר יותר לקהל מאשר לעצמי. שיקשיבו למלים ואלה יהיו להם למזור ונועם. שאדע להתחבר לכאן והעכשיו ולחבק את הרגע הזה. ושיותר מכול אזכה להשפיע בשירתי אהבה וחיבור למקום שממנו נוצר החוסר ששירים יכולים למלא.
      </prayer>
    </item>

    <item>
      <type>alef</type>
      <person>חיים באר, סופר</person>
      <prayer>
       במרוצת עשר השנים האחרונות חזרתי שבע פעמים לאוורוץ' – עיירה אוקראינית במחוז ז'יטומיר, ששם נולד אבי.
הקהילה היהודית במקום עברה שורה ארוכה של טלטלות: פרעות פטליורה, השלטון הקומוניסטי העריץ, השואה. כיום כבר לא נותר דבר. כל מוסדות הקהילה היהודית נהרסו. בית הקברות הישן, רוב בתי היהודים, בית הכנסת, בית המדרש – הכול נחרב.
כשאני בא לשם, אני בא רק לנ"צ. 
אני יודע בקירוב איפה היה בית הכנסת. שם, במקום החרב, ללא תקרה, ללא גג ואפילו ללא רצפה, אני עומד ומצרף את תפילתי לתפילותיהם של סבי וסבתי, בניהם – ובהם אבי – ויתר בני קהילתם. התפילה הזאת, במקום שהוא רק מקום וכשאני עומד לפני המקום, היא אולי התפילה המשמעותית ביותר שחוויתי.
      </prayer>
    </item>

    <item>
      <type>alef</type>
      <person>ארז ביטון, משורר</person>
      <prayer>
תָּבוֹא תְּפִלָּה בָּאֲפֵלָה
לְנֶפֶשׁ שְׁפָלָה  
יָבוֹא צֹהַר בַּשַּׁעַר הַנָּעוּל
יַקִּישׁ
בַּדֶּלֶת הַכְּפוּלָה
(מתוך "בית הפסנתרים" 2015)

אי-אז בגיל עשר, בבית כנסת קטן הקרוי "בית הכנסת של אמא רחל", באמצע שכונת עולים חדשים ממרוקו בעיר לוד. ראש השנה, ידי הקטנה בתוך ידו הגדולה של אבא ואני ילד שאין בו דיבור, נעתקו ממני המלים ואני כולי רטטים-רטטים, צועד אל בית הכנסת. שם, אני יודע, נכונה לי התרגשות הפוקדת אותי מדי שנה. 
בית הכנסת על שם אמא רחל הוא עכשיו שני קירות נפולים. בולדוזרים של עמידר באו עליו מאחור בעורמה של מתגנבים והיכו בו. כך עשו לכל השכונה, ואנשים שקמו בבוקר ראו שביתם נעשה חצי בית ועברו על כורחם לצריפים רעועים בקצה הרובע, כדי לעבור מאוחר יותר לשכונה מדולדלת עוד יותר. 
אבל אז, כשבית הכנסת של אמא רחל עמד על תלו, שני חברי לילדות, האחים אהרן ושמעון בן חמו, לקחו להם "חזקה" בראש השנה לקרוא בקהל את הפיוט "עת שערי רצון" ואת הפיוט "שפל רוח". אני, שהייתי קטן מהם בשנתיים-שלוש, הייתי נמלא קנאה ופיללתי בלבי שיום אחד אוכל גם אני לעמוד בקהל ולקרוא את השורות המטלטלות:
שְׁפַל רוּחַ, שְׁפַל בֶּרֶךְ וְקוֹמָה / אֲקַדֶּמְךָ בְּרֹב פַּחַד וְאֵימָה / לְפָנֶיךָ אֲנִי נֶחְשָׁב בְּעֵינַי / כְּתוֹלַעַת קְטַנָּה בָאֲדָמָה 
אהרן בן חמו נפל במלחמת ששת הימים. מאז אני בתחושה שבעצם הוא קרא כל הזמן את שיר העקדה של עצמו. ומאז קולו היה מהדהד באוזני מדי שנה, שם, בבית הכנסת הקטן על שם אמא רחל. אחיו שמעון המשיך לקרוא את "שפל רוח".
ריח הספסלים העתיקים, הד הקירות וקולו של החזן הזקן חיברו אותי למשהו שהוא מעבר לזמן. ושוב "שפל רוח" ושוב פחד ואימה מהולים בכמיהה שאין לה סוף.
      </prayer>
    </item>

    <item>
      <type>alef</type>
      <person>מל ברוקס, קולנוען ובדרן</person>
      <prayer>
מתוך "להאמין בַּכאילו: ראיון עם מל ברוקס", דן ליברגר

בתי הקולנוע שהקרינו סרטים אילמים בקוני איילנד הביאו את ברוקס לתגלית שליוותה אותו כל חייו. "היינו הולכים לשם וקונים נקניקייה, בירה שחורה ותירס שבושל למוות אצל פלדמן'ס, שהיה שם לפני נייתן'ס פיימוס הוט דוגז. מאחור היה להם קולנוע לסרטים אילמים.
"המסך היה רק סדין לבן. היתה להם מכונה כזאת, מהבהבת. זו היתה הפעם הראשונה שראיתי את המלאך הזה, לבן הפנים ויפה העיניים. ידעתי שזה היה משהו מיוחד. זו היתה הפעם הראשונה שראיתי [את קיטון]. הוא חבש כובע שנראה כמו לביבה והיה חינני במידה שלא תיאמן.
"דת אף פעם לא דיברה אלי, אבל התפללתי לסרטים אילמים. זה היה הקשר שלי עם דברים רוחניים. הייתי מגיע לשם מתי שרק יכולתי. למען האמת, הייתי מתפלח לשם וצופה בסרט בלי לקנות נקניקייה או קניש."
      </prayer>
    </item>

    <item>
      <type>alef</type>
      <person>ציפי גון גרוס, סופרת ואשת רדיו</person>
      <prayer>
ארבעים בני הדור הראשון, השני והשלישי עומדים בחרדת קודש בבית הכנסת הגדול של דובנא. את פנינו מקדם שלט שהציבו "שרידי הקהילה היהודית הדובנאית בשנת 2005 לזכר נשמות הקדושים והטהורים שנרצחו בידי הנאצים."
במשך שנים שימש המבנה מוסך. האוקראינים פרצו את קיר ארון הקודש לטובת כניסת המכוניות, ליד כותל המזרח חפרו בור כדי להציץ מלמטה אל הקרביים שלהן, את ציורי הקיר הקטנטנים כיסו בסיד. כך, בלי כוונה, שימרו אותם. השנים לא פוגגו את ההוד המבצרי. 
כאן עלה אבא שלי לתורה בבר המצווה שלו, כאן התפלל מדי בוקר סבא שלי, שרק לפני כמה שנים ראיתי לראשונה תמונה שלו. מכאן יצאו אל מותם שנים-עשר אלף יהודי העיירה חודש לפני שאבא ואמא ברחו אל היער.
לשלשת היונים ממלאת את עזרת הנשים, אבל אני לא מריחה אותה. באפי עולה ריח הטבק שאבא שלי, שלמה גון, קיבל ביום הכיפורים משרשרת הגברים המתפללים בשטיבל ברחוב ברדיצ'בסקי וקירב אל פני. ניחוח הטבק העז, מהול בריח הסבון העדין שבקע מאצבעותיו, מציף אותי, מצטרף ל"אבינו מלכנו" שבלב.
      </prayer>
    </item>

    <item>
      <type>alef</type>
      <person>איירה גלאס, שדרן ועיתונאי</person>
      <prayer>

אף שקיבלתי חינוך יהודי טוב, אני כבר לא מאמין באלוהים וכבר לא מתפלל. אם בכלל, בפעמים המעטות שבהן ביקרתי בבית הכנסת בזמן האחרון חשבתי בעיקר כמה מוזר זה, שבמשך אלפי שנים העלינו את אותו הצגה בכל שבוע, נאספנו לומר שוב ושוב אותן מלות שבח לאלוהים. אני לא בטוח שאני מבין את הרעיון הזה, אלוהים שזקוק לשבחים כאלה כמו מין מלך ימיביניימי אכזר שצריך שכולם יתייצבו לפניו ויכרעו ברך. כשאמרתי קדיש על אמא שלי, ודיקלמתי את העברית בעל פה, תמהתי על כך שברגעי היגון הכבד ביותר שלנו, הקדיש הוא פשוט דברי שבח לאלוהים. אני יודע שיש אנשים שמוצאים בזה נחמה. הלוואי שהייתי אחד מהם.
      </prayer>
    </item>

    <item>
      <type>alef</type>
      <person>דוד דאור, זמר</person>
      <prayer>
השירה היא הדרך שלי לחוות את התפילה במלוא עוצמתה הרוחנית. במופע שלי משולבות כמה תפילות, אך לפעמים גם מלים שאינן מגיעות מן המקורות הן עבורי כתפילת הלב: אני עוצם עיניים, הניגון פורט על כל נימי הגוף, הקהל ואני הופכים להיות אחד, עוצמת הביחד אוחזת בי ואני מרגיש כל נשימה באולם. 
באחד המופעים, ביפן, שרתי את השיר "פרפר", המדבר על חופש אמיתי. המופע התקיים ביער מקסים בעיירה הקטנה שירטקה. אני זוכר שתוך כדי שירה התפללתי שאצליח להרגיש משוחרר באמת מן השעבוד ליצרים וממשקעי העבר. ברגע ששרתי את המשפט "עוד מעט אתה פרפר" הגיח מבין העצים פרפר לבן ענק והתיישב לי על החזה, מעל הלב. 
      </prayer>
    </item>

    <item>
      <type>alef</type>
      <person>אלן דרשוביץ, משפטן וסופר</person>
      <prayer>
מתוך "על הדוכן: חיי בחוק" 

אני צריך להודות לבית הכנסת המקומי שלי, שעזר לי לגלות את הסקס. אני משוכנע שכוח עליון כלשהו הציב את הספסלים בדיוק בזווית הנכונה כדי לעורר לראשונה רגשות מיניים, ובדיוק ברגע הנכון. כאשר יהודים אורתודוקסים מתפללים, הם מתנודדים קדימה ואחורה בעמידה. כשהגעתי לגובה מסוים, החלק העליון והמעוקל של הספסל מולי היה מקביל בדיוק לאיבר המין שלי. את ההתעוררות המינית הראשונה שלי חוויתי בזמן ההתנודדות קדימה ואחורה בבית הכנסת.
      </prayer>
    </item>

    <item>
      <type>alef</type>
      <person>נחצ'ה היימן, מוסיקאי</person>
      <prayer>

בזמן האחרון אני מתפלל לבורא עולם שיתן לי עוד שנתיים לגמור את כל העבודות שלי. בעיקר אני רוצה להספיק לעשות סדר בשירים ישנים, שעוד לא ראו אור, אבל בינתיים הדברים מתווספים ולא תמיד יש זמן. 
כל כך הרבה עבודה – ואין לי למי להשאיר אותה. 
בינתיים שברתי צלעות וירך. אבל אני אחלים, אמשיך לעבוד על השירים שלי ואוציא אותם. אני כבר בן 82 וחצי, ואחרי זה לא אכפת לי ללכת: לעלות לגן עדן אל נתן יהונתן ועוד חברים שלי.
      </prayer>
    </item>


    <item>
      <type>vav</type>
      <person>אהרן וולף</person>
      <prayer>

אני עומד בחדר בית החולים שלפני רגעים ספורים היה מלא צעקות רופאים וצווחת אזעקות.
"יש לך תינוק חזק," אומרת המיילדת ומניחה שתי ידיים על כתפי, כאילו כדי לייצב אותי. "הוא יהיה בסדר."
אבל לא אכפת לי מבני שטרם נולד. אני עדיין לא מכיר אותו. "מה עם אשתי?"
"היא לוחמת." היא נכנסת לחדר הניתוח ואני נשאר לבדי.
ברגע הזה אני לא מתפלל. אני לא יודע איך או אל מי. במקום זאת אני ממתין. אני ממתין שניתוח החירום הקיסרי יסתיים. אני ממתין בפחד. *מה אם נעמי לא תהיה בסדר?*
אחר כך, אחרי שההרדמה של אשתי פגה והאדרנלין שלי התפוגג, אני מביט באבא שלי מחזיק את הבן שלי בפעם הראשונה. אבא שלי קורן אל דייגו ולוחש, "הוא ביטוי מושלם של גוף ושל אנרגיה." דמעות ממלאות את עיני. 
"ברוך אתה אדוני," אני מתחיל בלחש. "שהחיינו וקיימנו..." לא משנה אל מי מופנות המלים. משנה להכיר ברגע שבו הייתי לאב. וכך אני חולק כבוד לרגע הזה, בכל לילה, לפני שדייגו נרדם. "לזמן הזה."
      </prayer>
    </item>

    <item>
      <type>vav</type>
      <person>ד"ר רות וסטהיימר, סקסולוגית</person>
      <prayer>
מתוך "במרוצת חיי: אוטוביוגרפיה", רות וסטהיימר ובן יאגודה

בכל לילה, לפני ששכבתי לישון, הייתי אומרת קריאת שמע, שהיא התפילה החשובה ביותר בדת היהודית: "שמע ישראל ה' אלוהינו ה' אחד". לאחר שאבי נלקח מאתנו הייתי מסיימת את התפילה במלים, "אלוהים היקר, שמור על אבא היקר שלי ושלח אותו בחזרה הביתה." עוד לפני שאבא הלך, אמא היתה שוכבת איתי במיטה, שניצבה בקיתון שינה צמוד לחדר של הורי, עד שנרדמתי. היא המשיכה לעשות את זה, אבל היה חסר לי לראות את אבא במיטה שלו, קורא או מתפלל. היו לילות שבהם נכנסתי למיטה עם אמא שלי, להתנחם.
      </prayer>
    </item>

    <item>
      <type>vav</type>
      <person>רוחמה וייס, חוקרת ומרצה לתלמוד</person>
      <prayer>
      בזיעת אפִּי 

וּכְשֶׁשּׁוּב יָצָאתִי מֵהַבַּיִת
(וּכְבָר אֵינִי זוֹכֶרֶת אִם הָיָה
זֶה מֻקְדָּם מִדַּי, אוֹ מְאֻחָר מִדַּי)
לָחַשְׁתִּי לְעֵינֵיכֶם הַמְאֻכְזָבוֹת 
אֶת הַסּוֹד:
יְלָדִים, "הַמּוֹצִיא לֶחֶם מִן הָאָרֶץ" זוֹ אֲנִי (אִמָּא
שֶׁלָּכֶם, עִם הַשֵּׂעָר הַמַּאֲפִיר, כְּאֵבֵי הַגַּב
וּמִכְנְסֵי הַגִּ'ינְס).
זוֹ אֲנִי שֶׁהוֹלֶכֶת לַעֲשׂוֹת אֶת עֲבוֹדַת הַבּוֹרֵא.
וּבוֹאוּ נְבָרֵךְ עַל כָּךְ
שֶׁיֵּשׁ לִי אֶת הָאֶפְשָׁרוּת הַזּוֹ.
כִּי יֵשׁ אִמָּהוֹת שֶׁפָּשׁוּט לֹא יְכוֹלוֹת
לְתַקֵּן לְיַלְדֵיהֶן
אֶת הַטֵּרוּף הָאֱלֹהִי,
וַאֲנִי כֵּן (תּוֹדָה לָאֵל) וְעַל כֵּן
גַּם הַיּוֹם אֲנִי הוֹלֶכֶת לְהוֹצִיא לָנוּ
לֶחֶם מִן הָאָרֶץ.

מתוך הפרק "סידור תפילה" בספר "אחטא ואשוב" 
      </prayer>
    </item>

    <item>
      <type>vav</type>
       <person>יצחק בשביס זינגר, סופר</person>
      <prayer>
מתוך ראיון שלא פורסם עם פיליס מלמוד

כשאני בצרות, אני תמיד מתפלל. והואיל ואני בצרות כל הזמן, אני מתפלל כמעט בלי הפסקה.
      </prayer>
    </item>

    <item>
      <type>vav</type>
      <person>אוהד חיטמן, מוסיקאי</person>
      <prayer>

אינני אדם דתי, אך אני אדם מאמין.
לפני כמה שנים למדתי לעומק את תפילת שחרית. קיבלתי השראה חזקה מאוד מהמנטרה של המלים "מודה אני", ובאחד הלילות נטולי השינה ומלאי חשבונות הנפש חיברתי "מודה אני" משלי: תפילה חילונית, שעיקרה הודיה על דברים שלא השגתי, הוקרה לנפילות ולכשלונות שלי, והודאה בפחדים ובמחסומים שבי. בלעדיהם לא הייתי חזק כפי שאני ולא הייתי מניע את עצמי קדימה, אל עבר האדם שאני מייחל להיות בכל יום.
מלות הפזמון ממחישות שה"מודה אני" אינו רק בין האדם למקום, אלא גם בין אדם לחברו, ויותר מזה, בין אדם לנפש שבו.
"מודה אני שכשלתי ונפלתי לפניך ופניך כמו חותם בי שלא תם בי – אתה בי."
      </prayer>
    </item>

    <item>
      <type>vav</type>
      <person>ח"כ דב חנין</person>
      <prayer>

אחת התפילות החשובות ביהדות היא תפילת הקדיש, הפוגשת אותנו ברגעים קשים במיוחד ואישיים במיוחד.
לכן מרגש אותי לשמוע אותה מושרת בפיו של הזמר האפרו-אמריקאי פול רובסון, בשירו "ההימנון החסידי של רבי יצחק לוי". השיר – שאותו ביצע לראשונה ב-9 במאי 1958, יום השנה לניצחון על גרמניה הנאצית – הוא שיר מחאה נגד אנטישמיות ונגד רדיפות ודיכוי. שיר שיוצא מהלב ונוגע בלב.
רדיפות ודיכוי היו גם מנת חלקו של רובסון עצמו, שהיה קומוניסט, שר בקול הבס העמוק שלו אינספור שירים למען צדק וחירות והותקף בתקופת מקארתי. גם בתקופתנו ובמחוזותינו, שהדיכוי לא זר בהם, צריכות להדהד המלים
יְהֵא שְׁלָמָא רַבָּא וְחַיִּים עָלֵינוּ
וְעַל כָּל יִשְׂרָאֵל
וְעַל כָּל הָעַמִּים
וְאִמְרוּ אָמֵן.
      </prayer>
    </item>

    <item>
      <type>vav</type>
      <person>רועי חסן, משורר</person>
      <prayer>
      יוצר האש 

התפוגג הפחד
להזדקן מבלי שיישאר בי שריד
מטירוף האש

האש שלך תיקוד
בנשמתי הזקנה

ברוך אתה ה'
המתיר את קפיצת האגרוף
מהלב

המבדיל 
בין אור לאור
בין שמש לשמש

ברוך אתה ה'
יוצר האש

בחיי
      </prayer>
    </item>

    <item>
      <type>vav</type>
      <person>אסא כשר, פרופסור לפילוסופיה</person>
      <prayer>
       תפילת הבנים

דמותו של רבי ישעיהו הלוי הורוויץ (שי"ח–ש"צ, 1558–1630) ריתקה אותי תמיד. הפליא אותי השם שנתן לספרו "שני לוחות הברית" (של"ה) והפליא אותי שנקרא בפי כול "השל"ה הקדוש".
אני זוכר את היום שבו קטע בדבריו עורר בי התרגשות מיוחדת. "לבי אומר", כתב בפתח "תפילת הבנים" שלו, "שעת רצון לתפילה זו בערב ראש חודש סיון, הוא החודש שבו ניתנה התורה". ערב ראש חודש סיון, כ"ט באייר, יום ההולדת שלי. באותו יום, מצאתי את עצמי מבטא באמצעות המלים של השל"ה הקדוש חלק מאהבת הבנים והבנות שבלבי:
"... תן לכולנו חיים ארוכים וברוכים... שיהא זרעי וזרע זרעי עד עולם זרע כשר... אך שלום ואמת וטוב וישר בעיני אלוהים ובעיני אדם... ותן להם בריאות וכבוד וכוח, ותן להם קומה ויופי וחן וחסד, ויהיה אהבה ואחווה ושלום ביניהם...".
      </prayer>
    </item>

    <item>
      <type>vav</type>
      <person>הרב ישראל בנימין לאו</person>
      <prayer>

היה זה בר"ח אדר התשנ"ג.
הגעתי עם אחי נפתלי זכרו לברכה לתפילת מנחה ליד הכותל המערבי, שעתיים לפני פתיחת הקלפי לבחירת הרב הראשי לישראל. הייתי אחד משלושת המועמדים לתפקיד. 
לא יכולתי שלא להיזכר בביקור הראשון שלי בכותל, שחל בשבוע של ט' באב התש"ה, ארבעים ושמונה שנים לפני כן. גם אז הגעתי לתפילת מנחה עם אחי נפתלי. זה היה לאחר עלייתנו ארצה, עולים ראשונים לאחר השואה. לא ידעתי צורת אות ולא ידעתי עברית, וכמובן שלא ידעתי להתפלל. את הקדיש על אבא ואמא הי"ד אמרתי מלה במלה אחרי אחי, בלי להבין. 
ארבעים ושמונה שנה אחר כך כבר הבנתי את משמעות התפילה, וביום ההוא נבעה תפילתי ממעמקי הלב בהודיה לקב"ה, שזיכה אותי לצאת מגיא ההריגה למקדש מלך עיר מלוכה. 
      </prayer>
    </item>

    <item>
      <type>vav</type>
      <person>רמי לוי, איש עסקים</person>
      <prayer>

אני מגיע להיכל בבית הכנסת,  מבקש שההורים שלי יהיו בריאים, שלא יזדקקו למתנת בשר ודם ושיזכו לראות נינים מכל נכדיהם.
מבקש שאני ואשתי נזכה לראות את ילדינו בחופתם ושנזכה לראות נכדים ונינים. שנזכה להיות בצד של האוהבים והעושים טוב לעם ישראל. מבקש תמיד לשמח אנשים ולהיות בצד של המשמחים, ושיצר הרע לא ישתלט עלינו.
בעיקר מודה לבורא עולם על כל מה שהוא נותן לי בכל רגע ורגע.
      </prayer>
    </item>

    <item>
      <type>vav</type>
      <person>ג'ו ליברמן, פוליטיקאי</person>
      <prayer>
הרב סולובייצ'יק לימד שאם אתה יודע שמישהו חולה ואינך מתפלל לרפואתו, זה ממש כאילו ראית אדם חולה נתון במצוקה ברחוב ופשוט חלפת על פניו. עד כדי כך יכול כוחן של תפילות להגיע, וזו הסיבה שבכל בוקר אני מתפלל להשבת בריאותם הטובה של הנמצאים ברשימת בני משפחה וחברים שחלו. שלושה מועדי תפילה שקטה ביום עוזרים לי להאמין שאלוהים באמת שומע את התפילות שלי. 
כך אני מקווה.
אבל יש דבר אחד שאני יודע בוודאות, והוא שאני עצמי שומע את התפילות שלי. והן מזכירות לי להיות אסיר תודה לאלוהים בפתח כל יום, לחשוב על מה שאני מקווה לעשות במהלך היום, ואז, בסוף היום, לראות שכך אכן עשיתי. מבחינתי, תפילות הן הגשר המחבר ביני לבין מציאות הנמצאת מעבר לקיום, להבנה ולזמן האנושיים, ועם זאת היא אמיתית בתכלית. וכך, בתפילה שאנחנו אומרים מדי יום, אנו מודים לאלוהים על כך שנתן לנו את הרצון להודות לו בתפילה.
      </prayer>
    </item>

    <item>
      <type>mem</type>
      <person>טל מוסרי, שחקן ומנחה</person>
      <prayer>

סוד אישי, שלא רבים יודעים: בכל בוקר (טוב, כמעט בכל בוקר) אני פותח את היום שלי בים. אני רץ, שוחה ובעיקר נמצא עם האלוהים שלי ומתפלל: תפילה אישית, לא קבועה, במלותי שלי. תפילה שהיא תודה על כל מה שיש לי בעולם ועל כל מה שיש לכולנו. תפילת תודה.
אני מדבר אל האלוהים שלי וכך מכוון את היום שלי שיהיה טוב יותר ונכון יותר. לא תמיד זה מצליח, אך הכוונה חשובה לי לא פחות. 
אני זוכר שהייתי מדבר אל אלוהים כשהייתי ילד. סיפרתי לו כל מה שעובר עלי, כמו לחבר טוב. דיברתי על הדברים השמחים והעצובים, המרגיזים והכואבים. 
כיום, בים, אני מרגיש את האלוהים במלוא הדרו. זאת פתיחה נהדרת ליום חדש. 
      </prayer>
    </item>

    <item>
      <type>mem</type>
      <person>גלוריה סטיינם, הוגה פמיניסטית</person>
      <prayer>
       מתוך ספרה "מהפכה מבפנים: ספר ההערכה העצמית"

הרגע ההוא בלובי במלון היה הרגע הראשון שבו עלתה על דעתי אפשרות קיומו של עצמי אחר, בריא יותר, השוכן בתוך כל אחד ואחת מאיתנו וממתין שנעודד אותו. מדובר בחוויה כה נפוצה ועזה, שכבר יש לנו ביטויים שגורים עבורה: "הפתעתי את עצמי" או "בעל כורחי". בספרו "האדום והשחור" כינה סטנדל את העצמי הפנימי בשם "ידיד קטן". ב"צבע ארגמן" של אליס ווקר, סילי כותבת מכתבים לחבר חזק ושמו אלוהים, אבל היא כותבת גם לכוח שבתוכה. ילדים יוצרים חברים דמיוניים, ואילו ספורטאים, מוסיקאים וציירים שואפים לתת ביצירתם ביטוי לעצמי האמיתי והספונטני הזה. מדיטציה, תפילה ויצירתיות – כל אלה הן דרכים רגילות לשחרר את הקול הפנימי. כאשר העצמי מזוהה, נאמד, מתגלה ומוערך, זו הרגשה של "קליק" – כאילו באמת ובתמים התחברנו למקור כוח השייך אך ורק לנו, אבל מתחבר לכול.
      </prayer>
    </item>

    <item>
      <type>mem</type>
      <person>שרה סילברמן, קומיקאית</person>
      <prayer>
       מתוך ספרה "מרטיבה במיטה: סיפור של אומץ, גאולה ופיפי"

הדבר הראשון שממש עבד היה מין מנטרה שהמצאתי והייתי אומרת לעצמי, כמעט בלי קול, לפני ששכבתי לישון. הייתי נותנת נשיקת לילה טוב לאמא ולאבא שלי ואז סוגרת את הדלת. בהתחלה זו היתה הרגשה מוזרה, לדבר בקול רם לבד בחדר. אבל מתרגלים:
אני לא ארטיב במיטה.
אני לא ארטיב במיטה.
אני לא ארטיב במיטה.
אני לא ארטיב במיטה.
אל תרטיבי במיטה.
אל תרטיבי במיטה.
אל תרטיבי במיטה.
אל תרטיבי במיטה.
בבקשה אל תרטיבי במיטה.
בבקשה אל תרטיבי במיטה.
בבקשה אל תרטיבי במיטה.
בבקשה אל תרטיבי במיטה.

כיום אני מבינה שמה ששמר עלי יבשה בלילות ההם לא היה המלים הטרום-התבגרותיות של המנטרה המאולתרת, אלא העובדה שזו היתה מין מדיטציה. מה שעזר היה עצם העובדה שהתרכזתי בדבר אחד במשך יותר מדקה. בטח זו היתה התכלית של ההיפנוזה עם ד"ר גרים, אבל זה גם עבד. זה היה משהו אחר. זאת היתה תפילה.
      </prayer>
    </item>

    <item>
      <type>mem</type>
       <person>דן בניה סרי, סופר</person>
      <prayer>
       תפילת אב על קבר בנו
 
אתה אשר אתה, שבראת את השמים וכל צבאם. את האמונה, את התקווה להאמין שהאדם אשר יצרת ביום השישי הוא סיבתך האמיתית לנפוש ביום השביעי.
אתה, שציווית על הנטיעות להיעשות יערות. על התינוקות למלא בהם חלומות. ששטפת את עולמך בארגמן הפרחים, ללמד שהעולם שבראת הוא הנפלא שבהישגים.
ואנו האמנו בחוסנך. שאתה אשר אתה לא תניח לאש לבוא בין הפרחים. לחרב בבשרם של תינוקות צוהלים. אתה, המקימי מעפר דל שלא על מנת להשיבו אליך שנית דרך אפר המדורות.
ואני, שבמצוותך הבאתי את בני לעולם. יפה כשושן בין החוחים, נקי כפיים כבדולח הערוגות. תינוק שמחיוכו, כך למדתי מנביאיך, יופיע המשיח – להיות מהר המוריה אור לגויים.
ואני, שמבכה בשעה נוראה זו את קברו של תינוקי – משיח שלא יגיע – אינני בא לקלל את מה שקלקלת. אף אינני בא לתהות על מה שבראת, אלא לתבוע, בשם דמו השפוך של תינוקי, שתכיר שהעולם אשר בראת אינו היפה שבעולמות.
זו התקווה, וזו אף התפילה. שתתעשת, אתה אשר אתה, ותברא שנית, אך הפעם במחשבה תחילה, עולם נקי ממדורות. תינוקות עמידים לחרבות. או אז, ורק אז, אכרע ברך בפניך, אתה אשר אתה, ואומר לך: "תודה על כל מה שבראת".
      </prayer>
    </item>

    <item>
      <type>mem</type>
      <person>אהובה עוזרי, מוסיקאית</person>
      <prayer>
גם לפני שחליתי האמנתי בתפילה, וכל בוקר אני קמה להתפלל. זה עושה לי טוב בחיים. המלים מדברות בעד עצמן. לאחר מכן אני קוראת תהלים. זה עוזר לנשמה שלי. אני חיה כשאני קוראת תהלים. להאמין בתפילה זה אושר פנימי – ובשבילי, עם כל מה שאני עוברת, אין תרופה יותר טובה. האדם חלש ותמיד מחפש חיזוקים. אני מוצאת אותם בתפילה לאלוהים. זה מרגיע את הנפש הכואבת ואת הלב הדואב. תמיד יש פחד בנשמה, והתפילה מחזקת את הגוף מכל צרה. ואם צרה בכל זאת באה, היא כבר לא מפחידה.
אני בסך הכול בן-אדם שמחפש את השקט הנפשי. המלים של התהלים מרגיעות את נימי לבי. על כך אני מודה לאלוהים כל בוקר. 
      </prayer>
    </item>

    <item>
      <type>mem</type>
      <person>ויקטור פרנקל, פסיכיאטר ניצול שואה</person>
      <prayer>
מתוך ספרו "האדם מחפש משמעות"

דורנו דור ריאליסטי הוא, לפי שלמדנו לדעת, מהו האדם באמת. אחרי ככלות הכול, האדם הוא אותו יצור שהמציא את תאי-הגז של אושוויץ; אבל הוא גם אותו יצור שנכנס קוממיות אל תאי-גז אלה ועל שפתיו תפילת שמע ישראל.

עברית: חיים איזק
      </prayer>
    </item>

    <item>
      <type>mem</type>
      <person>אהרן צ'חנובר, ביוכימאי זוכה פרס נובל</person>
      <prayer>

בקיץ 2006 הגעתי עם בני לכינוס מדעי בפורטוגל. בשיטוטינו בסביבה מצאנו, בכיכר הכנסייה ובית העירייה, שלט המורה לכיוון בית הכנסת. פנינו לשם. השלט בחוץ סיפר שבית הכנסת נוסד במאה ה-15 אך נסגר לקראת סופה בצו האינקוויזיציה. שנים מעטות קודם לכן, לאחר נפילת המשטר הטוטליטרי בפורטוגל, שופץ ונפתח מחדש. 
בית הכנסת היה מבנה קטן ובו חדר אחד. כתבנו בספר המקום הקדשה בעברית ובאנגלית ויצאנו. אחרינו יצא השומר של בית הכנסת, שראה את שכתבנו בעברית. הוא קרא לנו לחזור וסיפר שהוא בן למשפחת מומרים שהתנצרו בשל לחץ הכנסייה וחיו דורות כנוצרים – כפי שעשו אז גם משפחות יהודיות רבות אחרות באזור. לפני כמה שנים, המשיך, גילה את יהדותו והתגייר. 
הוא הזמיננו לחזור לבית הכנסת למחרת ולהשתתף בטקס חנוכתו מחדש. כך עשינו, ואיתנו יהודים לא מעטים שהתקבצו מכל הסביבה. הטקס כוון לשהותי במקום כחתן פרס נובל ישראלי-יהודי, והיה לי כהפתעה מרגשת עד דמעות.
      </prayer>
    </item>

    <item>
      <type>mem</type>
      <person>מרגלית צנעני, זמרת</person>
      <prayer>

סבתי אם אבי היתה אוטודידקטית. בתימן היתה מציצה אל בתי כנסת ושומעת תפילות, ולאחר שמשפחתה עלתה לארץ, ב-48', היא התחילה ללמוד עם הילדים הקטנים והפכה ללמדנית, יודעת חומש וגמרא.
סבתא אמרה לנו שאי-אפשר לישון בלי לקרוא קריאת שמע שעל המיטה. אחיותי ואני היינו מניחות את אצבעות יד ימין על ארובות העיניים העצומות ואומרות, "שמע ישראל ה' אלוקינו ה' אחד". אי-אפשר לישון בלי הברכה, בלי ההגנה.
בבוקר היינו קמות, מזדקפות, נוטלות ידיים, שוטפות פנים ומברכות "מודה אני לפניך מלך אל חי וקיים שהחזרת בי נשמתי". הלכנו לישון בלי לדעת מה יקרה, ובכל זאת קמנו ליום חדש. על כך אני מודה לאל גם היום, ואת החינוך הזה קיבלתי מסבתי צביה (רזלה). 
      </prayer>
    </item>

    <item>
      <type>kuf</type>
      <person>פרנץ קפקא, סופר</person>
      <prayer>
       מתוך "מחברות האוקטבו"

הענווה מעניקה לכל אדם, גם למי שנואש בבדידותו, יחס עז מכל לזולת, וזאת לאלתר, אם כי רק כשהענווה היא ענווה גמורה ומתמדת. היא מסוגלת לכך משום שהיא שפת התפילה האמיתית, סגידה וברית איתנה כאחד. היחס לזולת הוא יחס התפילה, היחס לעצמך – יחס השאיפה; מן התפילה אתה שואב את הכוח לשאיפה.

עברית: שמעון זנדבנק
      </prayer>
    </item>

    <item>
      <type>kuf</type>
      <person>נעה רבן, שחקנית ובמאית</person>
      <prayer>

התפללתי לאהבה ללא תנאי: לילד או ילדה משלי, שיהיו איתי מעתה ועד הסוף וגם אחריו, כי בימינו אהבה באה והולכת בלי התראה. 
ואז הוא הגיע. ילדתי בן. 
ידעתי שמעכשיו לא אהיה לבד אפילו לרגע. לא אפחד שילך, לא אראה בכל פיתוי איום, לא אהסס לשחרר ולראות אותו פורח, לא אתנגד לפרידה זמנית כי תמיד-תמיד הוא יחזור. 
גיליתי שיש תפילה מובנית בתוך גוף של הורה: שהילד הזה ירגיש טוב בעולם, שימצא ביטחון ואומץ, שיאמין בעצמו, שיסמוך על מי שראוי לכך, שיהיה לו טוב ומשמעותי. תפילה לאושר עבור מי שגורם לי להרגיש אמיצה, בטוחה ואוהבת ללא תנאי.
      </prayer>
    </item>

    <item>
      <type>kuf</type>
      <person>רני רהב, יחצ"ן</person>
      <prayer>

כשנולד בני רועי הבטחנו לעצמנו, רעייתי הילה ואני, שאת בר המצווה שלו נציין בבית הכנסת האשכנזי בית יהודה בשכונת התקווה בתל אביב. זה היה בית הכנסת שאליו לקח אותי מדי שבת סבי המנוח, שמחה אבנון ז"ל, כשהייתי ילד. בית הכנסת האשכנזי היחיד בשכונת התקווה.
סבתי רחל וסבי גרו ביד אליהו. השביל שלצד ביתם הוביל את המתפללים לבית הכנסת וחיבר את יד אליהו לשכונת התקווה. הפרוכת על ארון הקודש בבית הכנסת הוקדשה לזכר דודי, מנשה אבנון ז"ל, אשר נפל במלחמת ששת הימים.
ביום שני, ג' בשבט התשס"ז, כשרועי בני קרא בתורה את פרשת "בא" והניח תפילין, הרגשתי כאילו כל החיים כולם התנקזו לרגע הטהור הזה: רגע פרטי, אך כזה המחבר את רועי ואותנו לכל עם ישראל ולקב"ה.
      </prayer>
    </item>

    <item>
      <type>kuf</type>
      <person>אלי רייטר, מחנך</person>
      <prayer>

עמדתי והתנודדתי בבית הכנסת. זה היה ביום כיפור ורציתי להרגיש מחובר. רציתי להרגיש משהו כשהתפללתי. להרגיש משמעות. אבל לא הרגשתי שום דבר. מן הפה שלי יצאו מלים ריקות.
בלילה ההוא יצאתי לרייב. באמצע הריקודים התחיל משחק בינגו. לקחתי שלושה כרטיסי בינגו וחיכיתי. אנשים סביבי התנודדו ואני עמדתי שם, הקשבתי למספרים והתפללתי לזכות בבינגו.
הפרס היה צעצוע של ילדים. כשהתפללתי לזכות, סוף-סוף הרגשתי משהו.
זה קרה.
זכיתי.
אבל גם הרגשתי משהו, סוף-סוף.
      </prayer>
    </item>

    <item>
      <type>kuf</type>
      <person>קארל ריינר, שחקן וקומיקאי</person>
      <prayer>
מתוך ספרו "אני זוכר אותי" 

אחרי הבר-מצווה הפיראטית שלי הרשיתי לעצמי להיות מגויס למניין וביליתי כל שבת בתפילה עם החברים הדתיים שלי. העמדתי פנים שאני קורא איזו תפילה שלא היתה הודות ליכולת שלי לדבר כמו-עברית. היכולת הזו שירתה אותי היטב שנים אחר כך, כשהצטרפתי לסיד סיזר הדגול והשתמשתי בכמו-צרפתית, כמו-איטלקית וכמו-גרמנית בסאטירות על סרטים זרים בתוכנית שלו.
החברים שלי ידעו שאני מדבר ג'יבריש, אבל לא גילו לאף אחד. חששתי שאם המבוגרים יגלו את זה, הם יעיפו אותי משם ויפקירו אותי לנפשי בסוף השבוע. שמחתי להיות חלק מהמניין, אבל הרגשתי אשמה נוראית בכל פעם שהייתי המתפלל העשירי. ידעתי שהזקנים הרגישו שאם אין לפחות עשרה יהודים שפונים לאלוהים במלים הקדושות והידועות, אלוהים לא ישמע אותם. חששתי שמשום שאני לא משתמש במלים מהתנ"ך אלא בכמו-עברית, מנעתי מתפילות של תשעה יהודים טובים להגיע לאוזניים של אלוהים.
אני יודע שחוק ההתיישנות כבר חל על פשע הנעורים הזה, אבל האשמה שלי בעינה עומדת.
      </prayer>
    </item>

    <item>
      <type>kuf</type>
      <person>ציפי שביט, בדרנית</person>
      <prayer>

בכל פעם לפני שאני עולה לבמה אני מתפללת עם שתי חברותי, "וִיהִי נֹעַם ה' אֱלֹהֵינוּ עָלֵינוּ וּמַעֲשֵׂה יָדֵינוּ כּוֹנְנָה עָלֵינוּ" – ומוסיפה, "בשם ה' נעשה ונצליח". רק אז אני עולה לבמה, ותמיד ברגל ימין.
רגע לפני שאני יורדת מהבמה, בזמן שהקהל עומד ומריע, אני עוצרת ואומרת לעצמי: זה לא ברור מאליו שהם עזבו בית ומצאו בייביסיטר וחניה ובחרו בי. אני מודה לאלוקים שהגרון החזיק מעמד ושאני לא צרודה ומודה לאלוקים על כל קרן שמש ואוכל ועל הכול ומאוד.
התפילה האישית שלי היא, "אל תיתן לי שום דבר חדש – ובעיקר אל תיקח ממני כלום."
      </prayer>
    </item>

    <item>
      <type>kuf</type>
      <person>מולי שפירא, איש רדיו</person>
      <prayer>

בית הכנסת שגדלתי בו הוא בית כנסת המרכזי לצפון ברחוב בן יהודה, פינת שדרות קק"ל. אני מתפלל שם מאז שאני זוכר את עצמי. אח שלי הגדול, בן 79, עלה שם לתורה. כמוהו אני ובני. שם ערכנו, כמובן, גם את הברית לנכדי, שנקרא על שם אבי. עד היום אני מתפלל בו מדי פעם בחגים ובשבתות.
בית כנסת הזה היה בית כנסת שכונתי. התפללו בו הרוקח של השכונה, הרופא של השכונה והמורה של השכונה: אבא שלי. כשהייתי בן עשר נהגנו לקשור את החזן בטלית שלו לבמה הקטנה שממנה שר. תעלולי ילדות. זה מה שהיה לנו כילדים: מגרש כדורסל, התנועה ובית הכנסת. 
רוב המתפללים בבית הכנסת היו אנשים מסורתיים-חילונים בנוסח אשכנז. היה לנו מנהג מיוחד, שנשמר עד היום, לשיר בסוף תפילת יום הכיפורים את "התקווה". 
בשלב מסוים נקלע בית הכנסת לצרות: הזקנים השכונתיים, הרוקח והקצב, מתו אט-אט, ולא היה מניין. בשנים האחרונות נכנסה למקום קבוצה של צעירים ספרדים ששומרים על התפילה בשביל הכבוד של הזקנים האשכנזים. הם פשוט עשו נס! בית הכנסת חזר לחיים והתמלא קהל. אני נותרתי יחידי מילדי בית הכנסת, מתרגש לשמוע שוב את "התקווה" בסוף תפילת יום הכיפורים. 
      </prayer>
    </item>


    <item>
      <type>yeled</type>
      <person>ילד כלשהו</person>
      <prayer>
       איזושהי תפילה של ילד כלשהו.
      </prayer>
    </item>

    <item>
      <type>a</type>
      <person>Kobi Aflalo - Singer</person>
      <prayer>
        Almighty God, first of all, I thank You for the privilege of singing to an audience that wants to listen. This is something that can never be taken for granted. I pray that You make my voice clear and that I direct my heart and truly give myself to my singing. That I will appreciate every moment and sing more to my audience than to myself. That they hear the words which will heal them and lead them to pleasantness. That I will know how to connect to the here and now and embrace the moment. And most of all, that I am worthy of bringing love through my songs and of filling the emptiness that only songs can fill.  
      </prayer>
    </item>

    <item>
      <type>a</type>
      <person>Yossi Alfi - Storyteller</person>
      <prayer>
Prayer
		 
From the day I learned to pray
I learned peace with myself.
I learned to receive and to give, to take and to cancel
my threats.

From the day I learned to pray
I learned doors to myself,
I learned to open and connect 
and to interpret my dreams.

(Translation by Marcela Sulak.
From the book Teviot Etzba Shel Ima)
 
      </prayer>
    </item>

    <item>
      <type>a</type>
      <person>Din Din Aviv - Singer</person>
      <prayer>
       I took a night taxi to the airport when leaving Uman (a city in Ukraine where pilgrims visit the grave of the Hasidic Rebbe Nachman of Breslov). The taxi driver stopped to refuel but his gas tank was frozen. We could not open the tank and had no choice but to go back to Uman and switch cars. It was two in the morning in this frightening, deserted place and I was alone with a driver who I did not know and who did not speak English. The snow outside was almost two feet high. The driver disappeared to search for a new vehicle, leaving me alone in the car. Five minutes passed. Then twenty minutes. I did not know if he would ever return. Should I get out of the car? Or lock myself inside? Should I leave a light on in the car? Is it better if they can see me or not? Great fear. The prayer that came out of me at that moment was a prayer of faith. I was in Uman. I was with my rebbe (rabbi); he would watch over me. I put my trust in him. I said, I am with the tzadik (the righteous one) and nothing can happen to me. All this time, I prayed. I recited all kinds of prayers, the Psalms, verses from the Torah – anything that I knew by heart – and I saw how it affected me, how it calmed me. These were moments of survival. 
      </prayer>
    </item>

     <item>
      <type>a</type>
      <person>Haim Be'er - Author</person>
      <prayer>
Over the last ten years, I have returned seven times to Ovruch – the Ukrainian town in the province of Zhytomyr where my father was born.

The Jewish community there was afflicted by many disasters: the Petliura pogroms, the tyrannical Communist regime, the Holocaust. Today, nothing remains. All Jewish institutions were destroyed. The old Jewish cemetery, Jewish homes, the synagogue, the beit midrash (religious study hall) – everything was wiped out. 
	 
When I go there, I am going only to a landmark, a waypoint.

I know roughly where the synagogue once stood. 

There, in that destroyed place that has no ceiling, no roof, not even a floor, I join my prayer to the prayers of my grandparents and their children – including my father – and to those of everyone else from that community. 

This prayer is in a place that is only a place. But because I am standing before The Place (before Ha-Makom, a name for God), it is perhaps the most meaningful prayer I have ever experienced.   

      </prayer>
    </item>

    <item>
      <type>a</type>
      <person>Dan Benaya Seri - Author</person>
      <prayer>
   		The Prayer of a Father at His Son's Graveside

You who are You, You who created the heavens and all the legions. It is my faith, my hope, to believe that the mankind You created on the sixth day is the true reason You rested on the seventh day.
		 
You who commanded the saplings to become forest and the children to dream dreams. You who washed Your world in crimson flowers, and showed the wonders of Your achievements to the world You created.
  
And we believed in Your strength. That You who are You would not let fire feast on your flowers. Not let the flesh of laughing babies burn. That You, who raised me up from the lowly dust, would not return me to You as ashes in the fire.

And I, just as You commanded, brought my son into the world. Beautiful like a lily among the thorns, innocent like the crystal of the flower beds. Whose smiles – so I learned from Your prophet – will hasten the arrival of the Messiah and bring forth from Mount Moriah light unto the nations.

And I, who wept at that terrible hour beside my baby's grave – the Messiah tarried. I did not come to curse Your curses or question what You have created. I do not even question the world that You created. But I do demand, in the name of the spilled blood of my baby, that You recognize this: the world You created is not the most beautiful of all worlds.

This is my hope and even my prayer. That You will be strong again, You who are You, and create again, but this time consciously, a world free from fire. Babies protected from destruction. Then, and only then, shall I kneel before You, You who are You, and give "thanks to You for all that You have created."
      </prayer>
    </item>

    <item>
      <type>a</type>
      <person>Erez Biton - Poet</person>
      <prayer>
Let come a prayer in the despair
to the lowly of soul.
Let come a crack
in the locked gate.
Let it strike
the double door.  

(Translation by Marcela Sulak.
From Beit Ha-Psanterim, 2015)

When I was ten, there was a small synagogue, in the middle of a Lod neighborhood of new immigrants from Morocco, called "The Synagogue of Rachel Imenu" (Rachel our Mother). It is Rosh Hashanah (Jewish New Year); my little hand is in the big hand of my father, and I am a child without speech. Speechless, the words inside me, the vibrating sounds and I walking to the synagogue. I know what awaits me, that I will feel the excitement I experience every year. 

The synagogue with the name of Rachel our Mother is now just two falling walls. Bulldozers from the Amidar Company crept up on it from behind, stealthily, and destroyed it. They did the same to the whole neighborhood.

People woke up to find that their house was now just half a house, that they had to move to ramshackle places at the edge of town, before they could be moved to another, even more run-down neighborhood.
 
But when the synagogue of Rachel our Mother still stood, it was the custom on Rosh Hashanah of my two childhood friends, the brothers Aaron and Shimon Ben Hamo, to recite to the congregation the piyyutim "Et Sha'arei Ratzon" and "Shefal Ruach" (the liturgical poems, "At this Hour, When the Gates of Favor Will Open" and "Lowly of Soul").  Younger by two or three years, I was filled with envy and I would pray in my heart that I too would one day stand among the congregation and recite those stirring lines:

Lowly of soul, lowly of knee and stature / I approach You with much fear and terror / Before You, I consider myself / Like a worm, small in the ground. 

Aaron Ben Hamo was killed in the Six-Day War. Since then, I have felt that he was actually always reciting the song of his own akedah (sacrifice). And since then, his voice echoes in my ear every year, there in the small synagogue with the name of Rachel our Mother. His brother Shimon continued to recite "Shefal Ruach."

The smell of the ancient benches, the echo from the walls, the voice of the old hazan (cantor) connect me to something beyond time. And, again "Shefal Ruach," and again, the fear and terror mix with a longing that has no end. 
      </prayer>
    </item>

    <item>
      <type>a</type>
      <person>Mel Brooks - Comedian</person>
      <prayer>
Thanks to silent movie houses on Coney Island, Brooks made a discovery that would stay with him for the rest of his life. 

"We'd go there, and we'd get a frankfurter, a root beer and a boiled-to-death ear of corn at Feldman's, which was before Nathan's Famous Hot Dogs. In the back, they had a silent movie theater.

The screen was just a white sheet. They had this flickering machine. That was the first time I saw this angel with a white face and these beautiful eyes. I knew this was something special. It was the first time I saw (Keaton). He wore a flat pancake of a hat, and I just couldn't believe the man's grace.

I never cared about religion, but I prayed to silent movies. It was my contact with things soulful. I'd go there as often as I could. I'd sneak in, actually, and watch the movie without buying the frankfurter or the knish."

From "Believing in Make Believe: An Interview with Mel Brooks" by Dan Lybarger
      </prayer>
    </item>

    <item>
      <type>a</type>
      <person>Aaron Ciechanover - Nobel Laureate</person>
      <prayer>
        In the summer of 2006, I attended a scientific conference in Portugal with my son. We were walking around a church square and town hall when we saw a sign pointing to a synagogue.  We followed it. The plaque outside the synagogue stated that it had been founded in the 15th century but closed at the end of that century by order of the Inquisition. The synagogue was renovated and reopened a few years back, after Portugal's totalitarian regime fell. 
		
The synagogue was a small one-room building. We signed the visitor's book in Hebrew and English and left. The guard saw that we had written in Hebrew and called us back. He explained that his family, like many in the area, were conversos – Jews who had been forced by the Church to convert – and had lived as Christians for many generations. He had recently discovered his Jewish roots and converted to Judaism.

The guard invited us to return the next day for a special ceremony. A number of Jews from around the area had gathered. To my shock, the ceremony was held in my honor as an Israeli-Jew who had recently won the Nobel Prize. I was surprised and moved to tears. 

      </prayer>
    </item>

    <item>
      <type>a</type>
     <person>David D'Or - Singer</person>
      <prayer>
       Singing is my way to experience the full spiritual force of prayer. My performances integrate some parts of the prayer service, although I find that some of the most heartfelt prayers do not come from traditional sources. I close my eyes, tuning in to every fiber of my body. The audience and I become one and, gripped by the strength of this unity, I feel every breath in the concert hall. 
	   
Once, in Japan, I sang the song "Parpar" (Butterfly), which is about true freedom. The concert was in a lovely forest in the small town of Shertaka.  I remember that, as I was singing, I prayed to break free from the bondage of my impulses and resentments. When I sang the words, "Soon, you will be a butterfly," a huge, white butterfly emerged from the trees and rested on my chest, above my heart. 
      </prayer>
    </item>

    <item>
      <type>a</type>
     <person>Alan Dershowitz - Lawyer</person>
      <prayer>
I need to thank my local synagogue for helping me discover sex. I am convinced that some higher authority built the benches at precisely the right height to introduce sexual feelings at precisely the right time. When Orthodox Jews pray, they shake back and forth while standing. When I reached a certain height, the top of the bench in front of me, which had a curve, was exactly parallel to my genitals. It was while shuckling back and forth in synagogue that I experienced my first arousal.

From "Taking the Stand: My Life in the Law" by Alan Dershowitz

      </prayer>
    </item>

    <item>
      <type>e</type>
      <person>Albert Einstein - Scientist</person>
      <prayer>
The Riverside Church
January 19, 1936

My dear Dr. Einstein, 

We have brought up the question: Do scientists pray? In our Sunday school class. It began by asking whether we could believe in both science and religion. We are writing to scientists and other important men, to try and have our own question answered.

We will feel greatly honored if you will answer our question: Do scientists pray, and what do they pray for?

We are in the sixth grade, Miss Ellis's class.

Respectfully yours,
Phyllis
----------------------

January 24, 1936

Dear Phyllis, 

I will attempt to reply to your question as simply as I can. Here is my answer:

Scientists believe that every occurrence, including the affairs of human beings, is due to the laws of nature. Therefore a scientist cannot be inclined to believe that the course of events can be influenced by prayer, that is, by a supernaturally manifested wish.

However, we must concede that our actual knowledge of these forces is imperfect, so that in the end the belief in the existence of a final, ultimate spirit rests on a kind of faith. Such belief remains widespread even with the current achievements in science. 

But also, everyone who is seriously involved in the pursuit of science becomes convinced that some spirit is manifest in the laws of the universe, one that is vastly superior to that of man. In this way the pursuit of science leads to a religious feeling of a special sort, which is surely quite different from the religiosity of someone more naive. 

With cordial greetings,
Your A. Einstein

From the book "Dear Professor Einstein: Albert Einstein's Letters to and from Children"
      </prayer>
    </item>

    <item>
      <type>e</type>
      <person>Viktor Frankl - Author</person>
      <prayer>
        Our generation is a realistic generation because we have learned what a human being really is. When all is said and done, man is that same creature who invented the gas-chambers of Auschwitz; but he is also that being who walked upright into those chambers with the prayer “Shema Yisrael” on his lips. 
      </prayer>
    </item>

    <item>
      <type>e</type>
      <person>Thomas Friedman - Journalist</person>
      <prayer>
One day during the summer of '82, when the Israeli siege of West Beirut was at its tightest, Mohammed spent an entire day walking around the city seeking to buy gasoline for our car – at $150 a thankful. Eventually he located a source of supply.

That night, as we drove home in darkness from the Reuters bureau, we were stopped on Hamra Street by two Palestinian guerrillas standing by a jeep. One was holding a gun and the other was holding an empty water bottle and a long rubber hose. They asked, very politely, whether they could suck a few gallons of gas from our tank to get their jeep going; it was out of gas. Mohammed, having spent an entire day scrounging around for our gasoline, was not going to give it up so easily.

Without blinking an eye, he began screaming that our tank was on empty, that we would be lucky to make it home, and if they did not believe him they could come over to his side of the car and look at the gas gauge themselves.

The gauge was resting comfortably of FULL. I couldn't believe what Mohammed was doing. I sat there stiff in my seat, with a stupid grin covering my face, praying to myself that one of the guerillas would not call Mohammed's bluff; fortunately, they believed him. When we drove away, I told Mohammed in a quivering voice that if we ever got stopped again by guerrillas looking for gas he should give them however much they wanted – otherwise I would suck it out of the tank myself. 

From his book "From Beirut to Jerusalem"

      </prayer>
    </item>

    <item>
      <type>e</type>
      <person>Ira Glass - Radio Personality</person>
      <prayer>
       Despite a good Jewish education I find I don’t believe in God anymore and don’t pray.  If anything, the few times I’ve gone to shul lately I’ve been struck at how strange it is that for thousands of years we’ve put on the same show every week, gathered to say the same words of praise to God over and over.  I’m not sure I understand this idea of a God who would need this praise, like some cruel medieval king who needs everyone to come before him on bended knee.  Saying Kaddish for my mom, reciting the Hebrew by heart, it’s confusing to me that in our moments of greatest grief the prayer is simply praise to God.  Of course I know people who find comfort in this.  I wish I did.
      </prayer>
    </item>

    <item>
      <type>e</type>
      <person>Tzipi Gon Gross - Author</person>
      <prayer>
     Forty members of the first, second and third generation stand reverently in the Great Synagogue of Dubno. We face a plaque established "by the remnants of the Jewish community of Dubno in 2005 in memory of the holy and pure souls murdered at the hands of the Nazis." 
	 
For years, the building was a garage. The Ukrainians broke through the wall where the aron kodesh (the Ark containing the Torah scrolls) stood to allow cars to enter. Near the synagogue's eastern wall, they dug a hole so that they could peer inside the vehicles. They unwittingly preserved the tiny frescoes by covering over them with plaster. But the years did not diminish the magnificence of this synagogue that feels like a castle. 

This is where my father was called to the Torah on his bar mitzvah, where my grandfather, whom I first saw in photos only a few years ago, prayed every morning. From here, the town's 12,000 Jews went to their deaths, one month after my father and mother had escaped to the forest. 

Pigeon droppings fill the women's section of the synagogue but I do not notice them. Rather, what rushes backs to me is the tobacco scent of my father, Shlomo Gon. It is the scent of the snuff that he received every Yom Kippur, which passed from person to person like a chain among the men at the shtiebel (small synagogue) on Tel Aviv's Berdichevsky Street. 

He would bring the snuff close to my face. I am flooded with memories of that pungent tobacco mingled with the delicate scent of soap that emanated from his fingers. In my heart, these memories merge with "Avinu Malkeinu" ("Our Father, Our King," a prayer recited on Yom Kippur).
      </prayer>
    </item>

    <item>
      <type>e</type>
      <person>Roy Hasan - Poet</person>
      <prayer>
	  Who Creates Fire
	  
The fear of the madness of the fire,
of growing old without anything
left of me, dissipates.

The fire will nod
in my old soul,

Blessed are You, G-d
Who from the heart 
allows a fist to leap,

Who distinguishes between light and light
between sun and sun.

Blessed are You, G-d
Who creates fire

in my life.

(Translation by Marcela Sulak)
      </prayer>
    </item>

    <item>
      <type>e</type>
      <person>Nachtshe (Nachum) Heiman - Songwriter</person>
      <prayer>
        Lately, I have been praying to the Creator to give me two more years to finish all my work.
		
Mainly, I want to publish any of my old songs that have not yet been brought to light. But I keep creating new material and don't have time to organize all the old work. 

So much work – and no one to leave it to. Recently, I broke my ribs and hip. But I will recover and continue to work on my songs. And I will publish them all.   

I am already past 82. After I finish my work, I won't mind if it's time to go up to heaven to be with the poet Natan Yonatan and my other friends. 
      </prayer>
    </item>

    <item>
      <type>e</type>
      <person>Ohad Hitman - Singer</person>
      <prayer>
       I am not a religiously observant person, but I am a believer. 
	   
A few years ago, I studied the morning prayers (shacharit) in depth. I was inspired by the words of "Modeh Ani" ("I am thankful to You"). One night, I could not sleep. I engaged in a cheshbon nefesh (an accounting of the soul) and composed my own version of "Modeh Ani". Mine was a secular prayer about being thankful for the things I am not, thankful for my falls and for my failings. I confessed my fears and the obstacles before me. Without these things, I would not be as strong as I am; they propel me forward every day and help me be the person I strive to be.

The words "Modeh Ani" guide the relationship between humans and God, and also our relationships with each other. Most of all, they connect a person to his own soul.

"I am thankful that I failed and fell down before you – and that your face is like a signature sealed within me, that you are in me."  
      </prayer>
    </item>

    <item>
      <type>e</type>
      <person>Franz Kafka - Author</person>
      <prayer>
Humility provides everyone, even him who despairs in solitude, with the strongest relationship to his fellow man, and this immediately, though, of course, only in the case of complete and permanent humility. It can do this because it is the true language of prayer, at once adoration and the firmest of unions. The relationship to one’s fellow man is the relationship of prayer, the relationship to oneself is the relationship of striving; it is from prayer that one draws the strength for one’s striving.

Taken from "The Blue Octavo Notebooks" (1954) by Franz Kafka.
      </prayer>
    </item>

    <item>
      <type>e</type>
      <person>Asa Kasher - Philosopher</person>
      <prayer>
	  Prayer for the Sons
	  
I have always been fascinated by the figure of Rabbi Isaiah HaLevi Horowitz (c. 1565–1630). I was amazed by the name he gave to his book – "Shenei Luchot HaBerit" ("Two Tablets of the Covenant"), commonly shortened to Shelah. I was also amazed that he was generally known, due to his authorship of this book, as the Shelah HaKadosh (the Holy Shelah).
		
I found some of the things he wrote especially inspiring. 

Introducing his "Prayer for the Sons" he writes: "My heart says that the eve of the Hebrew month of Sivan (erev Rosh Hodesh Sivan) is a propitious time for prayer, for the Torah was given in the month of Sivan." My own birthday is on the eve of Rosh Hodesh Sivan, i.e. the 29th day of the Hebrew month of Iyar. On this day, I find myself expressing, through the Holy Shelah's words, some of the love towards the sons and daughters that are in my heart. "Grant us all long lives and blessings … and may my children, and my children's children, and each generation of their children for ever be pure … with peace and truth, that they be good and honest in the eyes of God and in the eyes of humanity … and give them health, honor and strength, and grant them esteem and beauty, grace and kindness, and may there be love and unity and peace between them." 
      </prayer>
    </item>

    <item>
      <type>e</type>
      <person>Dov Khenin - Member of Knesset</person>
      <prayer>
       The Kaddish (the mourner's prayer) is one of the most important Jewish prayers, especially because we come across it during the hard times in our personal lives. 
	   
I was therefore excited to hear it sung by the African-American singer Paul Robeson as part of his song "The Hassidic Chant of Levi Isaac." The song – which he performed for the first time on May 9, 1958, the anniversary of the victory over Nazi Germany – is a protest song against anti-Semitism, persecution and oppression. The song comes from the heart and it touches the heart. 

Robeson himself suffered from oppression and persecution. He was a communist who, with his deep bass voice, performed countless songs for justice and liberty. He was blacklisted during the McCarthy era. Also in our time and in our region, where repression is no stranger, the words of the Kaddish still resonate:

May there be abundant peace and life for us
And for all Israel
And for all the nations
And let us say, Amen.
      </prayer>
    </item>

    <item>
      <type>l</type>
      <person>Rabbi Yisrael Meir Lau</person>
      <prayer>
      It was the beginning of the month of Adar, 1993 (Rosh Hodesh Adar, 5753 in the Hebrew calendar).
	  
I arrived at the Western Wall in Jerusalem with my brother Naphtali – may his memory be blessed – for the afternoon prayer (minchah). It was two hours before the ballot to select the Chief Rabbi of Israel. I was one of three candidates for the post.

I could not but remember my first visit to the Western Wall, forty-eight years earlier, in 1945, during the week of Tisha B'Av (the fast of Av). Then too, I came with my brother Naphtali for afternoon prayers. We had just made aliyah (immigrated) to Israel with the first immigrants after the Holocaust.

I did not know the Hebrew letters, I did not know Hebrew and, of course, I did not know how to pray. I said the kaddish (mourner's prayer) for my father and mother –may their memories be blessed – without comprehension, repeating after my brother every word he said. 

Forty-eight years later, I understood the meaning of prayer. On that day, my prayer came from the depths of my heart and was of gratitude to the Holy One, Blessed be He, for taking me out of the Valley of Death and bringing me to the King's Temple in His royal city.
      </prayer>
    </item>

     <item>
      <type>l</type>
      <person>Rami Levy - Retail Magnate</person>
      <prayer>
        I come to the synagogue and ask that my parents be healthy, that they not need to depend on gifts from human hands, and that they merit to see their grandchildren provide them with great-grandchildren.
		
I ask that my wife and I merit to see our children at the wedding canopy and that we are granted grandchildren and great-grandchildren. That we are always on the side of those who love and do good for the Jewish people. And I ask always to make people happy, and to be on the side of those who bring happiness, and that our evil inclination should not rule over us. 

And especially, I thank the Creator for everything He gives me each and every moment. 
      </prayer>
    </item>

    <item>
      <type>l</type>
      <person>Joe Lieberman - Politician</person>
      <prayer>
     Rav Soloveitchik taught that if you know someone is sick and you do not pray for their recovery, it is as if you see someone take ill on a street and just walk right by them. That is how powerful prayers can be, and why I pray every morning for a return to good health by a list of family and friends who are sick. 

Our thrice daily silent devotion helps me to believe that God really does hear my prayers. 

I hope so. 

But one thing I know for certain is that I hear my prayers. And they remind me to be grateful to God when I begin every day, to think about what I hope to do during the day, and then to see, at the end, how I did. To me, prayers are the bridge that connects me with a reality that is beyond human existence, understanding, and time and yet is absolutely real. As one of the daily prayers says, thank you God for inspiring me to thank you through prayer.
      </prayer>
    </item>

    <item>
      <type>l</type>
      <person>Tal Mosseri - Actor</person>
      <prayer>
         Here's a little secret that not many know: every morning (okay, almost every morning), I start my day at the sea. I run, I swim and I am fully with my God. And I pray, not fixed prayers, but my own words, a personal prayer.

My prayer is one of thanks for all I have in this world and all that we have. It is a prayer of thanks. I speak to my God and direct my day toward goodness. It does not always work, but for me the intention is just as important as the result. 

I remember talking to God when I was a child. I would speak to Him, like a good friend, about all the things I was going through. I would talk about the happy things and the sad, the annoying and the painful. 

Today, by the sea, I feel God in all His glory. It's a great start to a new day. 
      </prayer>
    </item>

    <item>
      <type>l</type>
      <person>Ahuva Ozeri - Singer</person>
      <prayer>
        Even before falling ill, I believed in prayer and would rise every morning to pray. Prayer makes my life better. The words speak for themselves. Afterwards, I read Psalms (Tehillim). They help my soul. I am alive when I read the Psalms. To believe in prayer is personal happiness – and that is the best medicine for what I'm going through. People are weak and need sources of strength. I find that strength by praying to God. It calms the mind and the aching heart. It quiets the fearful soul and protects the body from all its troubles. And if trouble does come, it is no longer frightening.
		
Ultimately, I am a person searching for inner peace. The words of the Psalms soothe my heart. For this, I thank God every morning.  
      </prayer>
    </item>

     <item>
      <type>l</type>
      <person>Noa Raban - Actor</person>
      <prayer>
        I prayed for unconditional love, for a boy or girl of my own, who would be there from now until the end, and also afterwards because in our days love comes and goes without warning. 
		
And then he arrived. I gave birth to a son.

I knew that from now on I would not be alone, not even for a moment. Not be afraid that he would go, not see threat in every temptation, not hesitate to let him go and watch him flourish. I would not mind being apart for a while, for he will always, always, return. 

I discovered that there is a prayer built into the body of every parent: that this child feel good in the world, find confidence and courage, that he believe in himself, only relying on those worthy of his trust, and that he find goodness and meaning. This prayer for happiness is for everyone who helps me feel brave and confident. It is for those I love unconditionally. 
      </prayer>
    </item>

    <item>
      <type>l</type>
      <person>Rani Rahav - Public Relations Leader</person>
      <prayer>
     When my son Ro'i was born, I made a promise to myself that my wife Hila and I would celebrate his bar mitzvah at the Ashkenazi Beit Yehuda Synagogue in Tel Aviv's Hatikva neighborhood. When I was a child, my grandfather Simcha Avnun, of blessed memory, would take me to this synagogue every Sabbath. It is Hatikva's only Ashkenazi synagogue.

Grandma Rachel and Grandpa lived in Yad Eliyahu.  Worshippers would walk to and from the synagogue via a path next to their house which linked Yad Eliyahu to the Hatikva neighborhood. The decorative curtain (parochet) covering the synagogue's Torah ark (the aron kodesh) was dedicated to the memory of my uncle, Menashe Avnun, who fell during the Six-Day War. 

My son Ro'i first put on tefillin and was called up to the Torah to recite the weekly portion "Bo" on Monday, January 22, 2007 (3 Shevat 5767 in the Hebrew calendar). I felt as if all of life was concentrated into this pure moment. It was a personal moment, but one that connected Ro'i and us to the Jewish people and to the Holy One, Blessed be He.      
      </prayer>
    </item>

    <item>
      <type>l</type>
      <person>Carl Reiner - Comedian</person>
      <prayer>
After my bootleg bar mitzvah, I allowed myself to be conscripted for the minyan and spent every Sabbath praying with my religious friends. I feigned reading whatever prayer was being offered by using my ability to "double-talk" Hebrew. That ability stood me well years when I joined the great Sid Caesar, using French, Italian, and German double-talk in satirizing foreign films on his television show.

My friends were aware that I was praying in gibberish, but they kept my secret. I feared that if the elders discovered this, they would throw me out, leaving me to fend myself on the weekend. I was happy to be a member of the minyan, but I suffered tremendous guilt each time I was the tenth man praying. I knew the old men felt that unless ten adult Jews entreated God with the prescribed holy words, God would not be able to hear them. I worried that because I was not using the Bible's words but Hebrew double-talk, I was keeping the prayers of nine good Jews from reaching God's ear.

I know that the statute of limitations may have run out on my adolescent crime, but not so my guilt.

From "I Remember Me " by Carl Reiner
      </prayer>
    </item>

    <item>
      <type>l</type>
      <person>Eli Reiter</person>
      <prayer>
        I stood in shul, swaying. It was Yom Kippur and I wanted to feel connected. I wanted to feel something when I prayed. To feel meaningful. But I felt nothing. Empty words exited my mouth.
		
That night I went to a rave. Amid the dancing, a bingo game started. I grabbed 3 bingo cards and waited. As people around me swayed, I stood there, listening for the numbers, praying to win the bingo game.

The prize was a children’s toy. I finally felt something as I silently prayed to win.

It happened.

I won.

But I also finally felt something.
      </prayer>
    </item>

    <item>
      <type>s</type>
      <person>Muli Shapira - Radio Personality</person>
      <prayer>
     I grew up attending the North Central Synagogue on Ben Yehuda Street in Tel Aviv, on the corner of Keren Kayemeth LeIsrael Boulevard. I've prayed there for as long as I can remember. This was where my oldest brother, who is now 79, was first called to the Torah. My son and I also celebrated our bar mitzvahs here. My grandson was circumcised, and named after my father, at this synagogue. I still pray there today, on holidays and the Sabbath.

It was a neighborhood synagogue. The local pharmacist and doctor prayed there. So did the neighborhood teacher: my father. When we were ten, we used to tie the cantor's prayer shawl to the bimah, the small stage from where he sang. Childhood mischief. Growing up, we had the basketball court, the youth movement and this synagogue. 

The congregation was mainly traditional-secular and followed the usual Ashkenazi prayer service. However, to this day we have a special custom of singing "Hatikva", the Israel national anthem, at the end of Yom Kippur prayers. 

At one point, the synagogue was struggling. The old neighborhood and its residents, like the pharmacist and the butcher, were no more. We could not get a minyan, a prayer quorum of ten men.  But recently, a new group of young Sephardim have kept the prayers going, preserving the honor of us aging Ashkenazim.

There is no doubt about it, they have performed a miracle! The synagogue has come back to life and is filled with new congregants. I am the only one from my childhood days still going to the synagogue. But I am still excited to hear "Hatikva" at the end of Yom Kippur prayers.
      </prayer>
    </item>

    <item>
      <type>s</type>
      <person>Tzipi Shavit - Actor</person>
      <prayer>
        Before I go on stage, two friends and I always pray: "May the Lord's pleasantness be upon us and let the work of our hands be established for us." And then we add, "In the name of the Lord, we shall do and we shall succeed." Only then, and always with my right foot first, do I step on stage. 
		
And just before I leave the stage, as the crowd claps and cheers, I stop and say to myself:  This is not something I take for granted. These people went out tonight, they found babysitters and parking spaces; they chose me. I thank God that my voice stayed strong and I was not hoarse. And I thank God for every ray of sunshine, for food, for every single thing and more.

My personal prayer is "Do not give me anything new, and especially do not take anything away from me."
      </prayer>
    </item>

    <item>
      <type>s</type>
      <person>Sarah Silverman - Comedian</person>
      <prayer>
The first thing that actually worked was this kind of chant I made up and I would say to myself, just barely out loud, before bed. I'd kiss my mom or dad goodnight and then shut the door. There is a weird feeling at first, talking out loud when you're alone in a room. But you get used to it:

I will not wet the bed.
I will not wet the bed.
I will not wet the bed.
I will not wet the bed.
Do not wet the bed.
Do not wet the bed.
Do not wet the bed.
Do not wet the bed.
Please do not wet the bed.
Please do not wet the bed.
Please do not wet the bed.
Please do not wet the bed.

I realize now that what kept me dry through those nights weren't my preteen lyrics to this makeshift mantra, but the fact that this was a kind of meditation. Just the fact that I was focusing on one thing for more than a minute, helped. It was probably the intention of the hypnotism with Dr, Grimm, but this thing worked. It was different. It was a prayer.

From her book "The Bedwetter: Stories of Courage, Redemption, and Pee"

  
      </prayer>
    </item>

	 <item>
      <type>s</type>
      <person>Isaac Bashevis Singer - Author</person>
      <prayer>       
Whenever I'm in trouble, I pray. And because I'm in trouble all of the time, I pray almost constantly.

Taken from an unpublished interview with Isaac Bashevis Singer by Phyllis Malamud
      </prayer>
    </item>

    <item>
      <type>s</type>
      <person>Gloria Steinem - Feminist</person>
      <prayer>
But even then, this moment in a hotel lobby was my first inkling that there is a healthier self within each of us, just waiting for encouragement. It's such a common experience of unexpected strength that we have ordinary phrases for it: "I surprised myself," or "In spite of myself." In The Red and the Black, Stendhal called this inner self "a little friend." In Alice Walker's The Color Purple, Celie writes letters to a strong friend called God, but she is also writing to the strength within herself.

Children create imaginary playmates, and athletes, musicians and painters strive to free this true and spontaneous self in their work. Meditation, prayer, creativity – all these are ordinary ways of freeing an inner voice. It's a feeling of "clicking in" when that self is recognized, valued, discovered, esteemed – as if we literally plug into an inner energy that is ours alone, yet connects us to everything.

From her book "Revolution from Within: A Book of Self-Esteem"
      </prayer>
    </item>

    <item>
      <type>s</type>
      <person>Margalit Tzan'ani - Singer</person>
      <prayer>
        My grandmother, my father's mother, was an autodidact. In Yemen, she would sneak into the synagogue to listen to the prayers. After her family made aliyah (immigrated) to Israel in 1948, she started studying, at first alongside small children. She eventually became knowledgeable in the Bible and Talmud. 
		
Grandma taught us it was impossible to sleep if you did not recite the Shema (a major Jewish prayer) before bed. My sisters and I would put our right hands tightly over our eyes and say, "Hear Israel, the Lord our God, the Lord is One." It was impossible to sleep without the blessing and protection of this prayer.

In the morning we would rise, our bent bodies now straight, and wash our hands and faces. Then we would say the prayer "Modeh Ani," thanking God for returning our souls taken during the night. We went to bed with our lives in the balance, but each morning we rose for the new day. I still pray today, thanks to what I learned from my Grandma Tsvia Raziela. 
      </prayer>
    </item>

    <item>
      <type>s</type>
      <person>Ruhama Weiss - Artist</person>
      <prayer>
        By the Sweat of My Brow 

And when I left home once more
(and I don’t remember anymore 
if it was too early or too late)
I whispered the secret to your 
disappointed eyes:
Children, “Who brings forth bread from the earth,” that’s me (their mother
with the graying hair, the aching back
and the denim jeans),
that’s me who goes to do the work of the Creator.
Come bless that, 
since I have that power,
because there are mothers who simply cannot       
repair for their children 
the madness of God. 
And I can (thanks to God) and so, yes,
today, as well, I am going to bring us forth
bread from the earth.

(Translation by Marcela Sulak.
From the chapter "Siddur Tefillah" in the book Acheta V'ashuv) 

      </prayer>
    </item>

    <item>
      <type>s</type>
      <person>Dr. Ruth Westheimer - Sex Therapist</person>
      <prayer>
Every night before going to bed I used to say the Shema, the most important prayer in the Jewish religion – "Hear, O Israel, The Lord Our God, The Lord Is One." After my father was taken away I would end the prayer by saying, "Dear God, watch over my dear sweet daddy and send him home."

Even before my father was gone, my mother used to lie with me in my bed, which was in a sleeping alcove off my parents' room, until I fell asleep. She still did so, but I missed seeing my father in his bed, reading or praying. Some nights I climbed into bed with my mother to be comforted.

From "Taking All in a Lifetime: An Autobiography" by Ruth Westheimer and Ben Yagoda
      </prayer>
    </item>

    <item>
      <type>s</type>
      <person>Elie Wiesel - Author</person>
      <prayer>
In days gone by, Rosh Hashanah had dominated my life. I knew that my sins grieved the Almighty and so I pleaded for forgiveness. In those days, I fully believed that the salvation of the world depended on every one of my deeds, on every one of my prayers.

But now, I no longer pleaded for anything. I was no longer able to lament. On the contrary, I felt very strong. I was the accuser, God the accused. My eyes had opened and I was alone, terribly alone in a world without God, without man.

Without love or mercy. I was nothing but ashes now, but I felt myself to be stronger than this Almighty to whom my life had been bound for so long. In the midst of these men assembled for prayer, I felt like an observer, a stranger.

From "Night" by Elie Wiesel
      </prayer>
    </item>

    <item>
      <type>s</type>
      <person>Aaron Wolfe - Educator</person>
      <prayer>
I'm standing in a hospital room that just moments before was a maelstrom of shouting doctors and screaming alarms. 

"Your baby is strong." The midwife puts both hands on my shoulders as though to steady me. "He'll be okay."

But I don't care about my unborn son. I don't know him yet. "What about my wife?"

"She's a warrior." Then she walks into the operating room and I'm alone. 

I don't pray at that moment. I don't know how to or who to. Instead, I wait. I wait for the emergency c-section to be over. I wait in fear. *What if Naomi isn't okay?*

Later, after my wife's anesthesia has faded and my adrenalin drained away, I watch my father hold my son for the first time. My dad beams at Diego and whispers, "he's the perfect expression of body and energy." And tears spring to my eyes. 

*"Baruch ata adonai...,"* I begin under my breath. *"Shehecheyanu, v'kiy'manu..."* To whom it's addressed is unimportant. Recognizing the moment that I became a father is. And so I honor that moment every night before Diego falls asleep. *La zman ha ze.*
      </prayer>
    </item>

    <item>
      <type>kid</type>
      <person>Coming soon</person>
      <prayer>
     
      </prayer>
    </item>

</prayers>